Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Theater Ephemera
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William A. Speck collection of Goetheana: theater ephemera
1725-1984
1829-1940
YCGL MSS 24
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(10 boxes) + 5 broadside folders
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Theater Ephemera consists of eighteenth- through twentieth-century theater playbills, programs, broadsides, posters, and other ephemera documenting performances of plays, operas, magic and puppet shows, burlesques and lectures based on works by Goethe (primarily Faust ) and other German and European writers and composers.
Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Most of the material in the Speck Collection was assembled by William A. Speck. Much of the Faust material probably came from the Ehrhardt Collection, purchased by the library in 1922. Additional items have been added more recently by the library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated Materials: William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6), William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Music (YCGL MSS 9), and William A. Speck Collection of Prints (YCGL MSS 11), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
William A. Speck (1864-1928)
William A. Speck, the son of German immigrants, was born in New York City in 1864. A pharmacist by profession, he amassed the largest Goethe collection outside of Germany. In 1913, he and his collection came from Haverstraw, New York to Yale, where he served as curator of the collection until his death in 1928. For further biographical information on William A. Speck and a general history and description of the Speck Collection, see the finding aid for the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts (YCGL MSS 6).
Scope and Contents
The William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Theater Ephemera consists of eighteenth- through twentieth-century theater playbills, programs, broadsides, posters, and other ephemera documenting performances of plays, operas, magic and puppet shows, burlesques and lectures based on works by Goethe (primarily Faust ) and other German and European writers and composers. The collection reveals the extent to which Goethe's work was popularized and incorporated into a wide range of theatrical and musical performance genres. While the majority of materials document performances in Germany, performances in other European and American cities are also represented. The collection also includes original catalogue cards which formerly served to provide access to the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Performances of Goethe's Works and Other Productions Based on Them, circa 1725-1984. II. Performances of Plays and Operas by Other Writers, 1759-1929. III Additional Playbills, Programs, Posters, and Other Ephemera, 1806-1934.
Magic shows -- Germany; Opera -- Germany; Puppet plays, German; Theater -- Germany; Playbills; Posters; Theater programs; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 -- Adaptations; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Faust); Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 ( Faust, Musical settings); Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832 -- Stage history; Speck, William A. (William Alfred), 1864-1928
- Performances of Goethe's Works and Other Productions Based on Them, circa 1725-1984; Series I; 2; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I. is organized into ten subseries: Faust in Europe without Music, Faust in Europe with Music, Faust in the United States, Operas Related to Faust, Faust by Others than Goethe, Faust as Burlesque, Magic Shows Related to Faust, Faust Puppet Plays, Works Based on Faust -Related Characters, and Goethe Works Other than Faust. Within each subseries material is arranged alphabetically by name of city, title of work, or creator of work.
  - Faust in Europe without Music, 1829-1932
    - Altenberg, Altonae, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Berlin, 1899-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Chemnitz, Coburg, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dresden, 1829-1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Frankfurt, Halle, Hamburg, Josefstadt, 1899-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Leipzig, London, 1829-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - München, Paris, Reichenberg, Weimar, 1908-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Wien, Zwickau, 1910-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Urfaust in Europe, 1900-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Eastern Europe, 1867-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faust in Europe with Music, 1856-1935
    - Berlin, Braunschweig, Breslau, Chemnitz, Coburg, Köln, 1896-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Darmstadt, Dresden, Düsseldorf, 1879-1935 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Frankfurt, Freiburg, Leipzig, 1856-1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - London, Meiningen, München, Plauen, Prag, Stuttgart, Teplitz-Schönau, 1866-1924 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Weimar, Wien, 1870-1928 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Zwickau, 1910-1915 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Faust in the United States, 1864-1947
    - Performances in New York, 1892-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Performances in Connecticut, Illinois, Massachusetts, Michigan, New Jersey, Ohio, Utah, and Washington, 1864-1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Operas Related to Faust, 1824-1930
    - Faust's Verdammung, by Hector Berlioz, 1854-1930 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Mephistopheles, by Arrige Boito, Doktor Faust, by Ferrucio Busoni, 1882-1925 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Faust, Faust und Margarethe, er Margarethe, by Charles Gounod, 1864-1928 (Box 3, Folder 22-25)
    - Don Juan, by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, 1837-1907 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Faust, by Louis Spohr, 1824-1860 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Faust by Others than Goethe, 1773-1934
    - Boeddicker - Wolzogen, unidentified, 1810-1934 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified authors, 1773-1900, undated (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Faust as Burlesque, 1825-1893, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Magic Shows Related to Faust, 1800-1912 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Faust Puppet Plays, circa 1725-1954
    - Altenberg - Dresden, 1812-1935 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Frankfurt - Löbau, circa 1725 - 1954 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
    - Mannheim - Zwickau, unidentified, 1807-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
    - Don Juan plays, Medea plays, Robert der Teufel, Christoph Wagner plays, Casperl plays, and Goethe groteske, 1808-1934,undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Works Based on Faust -Related Characters, 1774-1912
    - Don Juan, 1856-1906, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Faust und Margarethe, 1854-1907 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Margarethl und Fäustling by Julius Hopp, Margarethe, and Dr. Faust's Zauberkäppchen, 1844-1904 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Der ewige Jude, Helena, Mephisto, and Tanzmärchen, 1774-1912 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Robert der Teufel, 1833-1897 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Goethe Works Other than Faust, 1775-1984
    - Clavigo and Egmont, 1849-1932 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Die erste Walpurgisnacht, Erwin und Elmire, Die Fischerin, Die Geschwister, and Goethe-Feier, 1775-1932 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - "Goethe in fiction" (Goethe as a character in productions), Götz von Berlichingen, Harzreise im Winter, and Iphigenia, 1849-1940 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Das Jahrmarktfest von Plundersweilern, Jery und Bätely, Laune des Verliebten, Lieder und Balladen, Mignon, and Die Mitschuldigen, 1849-1932 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Die natürliche Tochter, Paläophron und Neoterpe, Pandora, Prometheus, Satyros, Stella, Torquato Tasso, Triumph der Empfindsamkeit, Was wir bringen, and Werther, 1802-1984 (Box 7, Folder 48)
- Performances of Plays and Operas by Other Writers, 1759-1929; Series II; 3
  This series is arranged alphabetically by name of author or composer.
  - Byron, Borngräber, Giordano-Bruno, Fuchs, and Hauptmann, 1860-1907 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Hell, Herzer und Löhner, Hiller, Hirschfield, Hölz, Ibsen, and Iffland, 1791-1928 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Klinger, Kotzebue, Lenz, Lessing, Rousseau, Sachs, Schiller, Strindberg, Wagner, and anonymous authors, 1759-1929 (Box 8, Folder 51)
- Additional Playbills, Programs, Posters and Other Ephemera, 1806-1934; Series III; 3
  This series is organized into three subseries: Lectures on Goethe, Miscellaneous Stage Productions, and Miscellaneous Puppet Plays. Lectures and Stage Production material is arranged alphabetically by the name of the city where presented; Puppet Play material is not arranged.
  - Lectures on Goethe, 1895-1929, undated (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous Stage Productions, 1908-1934 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous Puppet Plays, 1806-1934, undated (Box 8, Folder 54)
- Objects
  - Toy theatre, undated; 13.5 x 15.5 x 4.25 inches (Box 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Paper and cardboard proscenium showing a scene from Faust, assembled from printed lithographic illustrations.
- Broadside Material
  Broadside Material consists of items from Series I through Series III as indicated in the above listing.
  - Broadside folder 55 (Box BSD, folder 55)
  - Broadside folder 56 (Box BSD, folder 56)
  - Broadside folder 57 (Box BSD, folder 57)
  - Broadside folder 58 (Box BSD, folder 58)
  - Broadside folder 59 (Box BSD, folder 59)
- Original Collection Catalogue Cards (Box 9)
  Original catalogue cards formerly served to provide access to the collection.